# MICHAEL "TED" O'CONNOR II

Hatfield, PA 19440 · 267-209-0029

resume@toconnor.com · https://www.linkedin.com/in/oconnor

Accomplished corporate executive and software engineer with over 20 years of experience with highly available enterprise solutions in regulated industries. Looking to leverage my proven technical, management, and communication skills in a new challenging opportunity.

# **EXPERIENCE**

#### MARCH 2000 - MARCH 2019

## DIRECTOR OF SYSTEM ENGINEERING, IQVIA, INC.

- Managed process to integrate Wingspan Technology into IQVIA post acquisition.
- Oversaw migration from legacy co-location data centers into Amazon Web Services.
- Led multinational team to increase responsiveness of production support.
- Developed architecture improvements to handle a 10X increase in client load.
- Facilitated Change Advisory Board to mitigate risks to running systems.
- Participated in client audits, RFP responses and new client on-boarding process.
- Prepared and tracked against annual department budget.

## CHIEF INFORMATION OFFICER, WINGSPAN TECHNOLOGY, INC.

- Created strategic direction to improve system availability and resiliency.
- Designed, implemented and oversaw the maintenance and support of the server infrastructure for numerous production SaaS offerings.
- Automated virtual server creation and configuration through Packer and Puppet.
- Established system wide monitoring and alerting to enable proactive issue responses.
- Streamlined ITIL and 21 CFR Part 11 compliant change control procedures with version control and code reviews for validated environments.
- Instituted new recruiting and interview processes to improve department staffing.
- Improved security practices with penetration testing, vulnerability scans and automated patches as acting Chief Security Officer.

## PRINCIPAL TECHNOLOGIST, WINGSPAN TECHNOLOGY, INC.

- Managed teams of software developers to meet delivery deadlines and quality metrics.
- Developed document management software to integrate Documentum with intranet portals like SharePoint, WebSphere, WebLogic and JBoss.
- Provided technical guidance to engineering, quality assurance, support, and sales teams.
- Led requirements gathering meetings with key business users and stakeholders.
- Created ability to cross-compile Java code into .NET libraries to increase code reuse.

## SENIOR SOFTWARE DEVELOPER, WINGSPAN TECHNOLOGY, INC.

- Designed and developed custom web applications for clients in the pharmaceutical, financial and power industries.
- Created data warehouse and web reports for financial investment tracking.
- Developed peer recognition award system for Fortune 500 pharmaceutical company.

#### **AUGUST 1997 - MARCH 2000**

# **SENIOR CONSULTANT, ERNST & YOUNG, LLP**

- Participated in an ERP selection process for the nation's largest grocery wholesaler.
- Trained home improvement store employees on the installation of CAD software.

# SKILLS

- Databases: PostgreSQL, MySQL, Oracle, SQL Server
  Languages: Java, SQL, Go, Ruby, Bash, .NET
- Automation: Puppet, Packer, Rundeck, Foreman
- Web: HTML, JavaScript, CSS, SSL, SAML
- AWS: EC2, RDS, ELB, S3, EFS, Glacier, Route 53
- Build: Git, Bamboo, Maven, Ant, Jenkins

- OS: CentOS/RHEL, MacOS, Windows
  - Monitoring: Splunk, Datadog, Zabbix, Sentry
- Virtualization: Docker, Vagrant, VMWare
  - Support: Jira, Zendesk, Pingdom, PagerDuty
- Apps: Apache, Tomcat, Solr, Zookeeper, HAProxy, LDAP, Hazelcast, SpiraTeam, Documentum

# **EDUCATION**

## **BACHELORS OF COMPUTER ENGINEERING, VILLANOVA UNIVERSITY**

- Graduated Cum Laude with top GPA in major. Honor Roll every semester.
- Member of Varsity Crew Team, ACM, IEEE, Tau Beta Pi and Eta Kappa Nu.

# **EXTRAS**

**OCTOBER 2009 - PRESENT** 

**BASKETBALL COACH, DEEP RUN VALLEY SPORTS ASSOCIATION** 

**MAY 2013 – OCTOBER 2016** 

BASKETBALL COMMISSIONER, DEEP RUN VALLEY SPORTS ASSOCIATION

**AUGUST 2010 - NOVEMBER 2016** 

FOOTBALL COACH, LENAPE VALLEY POP WARNER

**DECEMBER 2005** 

**AUTHOR, DR. DOBB'S JOURNAL** 

"Object-Relational Mapping in Java with SimpleORM"

**OCTOBER 2005** 

**AUTHOR, DR. DOBB'S JOURNAL** 

"Developing JSR-168 Portlets"

**AUGUST 2004** 

SPEAKER, PHILADELPHIA JAVA USERS GROUP

"Developing High Performance Web Services using Apache Axis"

**JULY 2002** 

**CERTIFIED JAVA DEVELOPER, SUN MICROSYSTEMS** 

**DECEMBER 2000** 

MICROSOFT CERTIFIED SOLUTION DEVELOPER, MICROSOFT